<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.bluepail.co//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.bluepail.co//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-15T17:55:47+00:00</updated><id>https://www.bluepail.co//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Blue Pail</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Building an app with Generative AI</title><link href="https://www.bluepail.co//2024/02/14/build-an-app-with-gen-ai.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building an app with Generative AI" /><published>2024-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.bluepail.co//2024/02/14/build-an-app-with-gen-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.bluepail.co//2024/02/14/build-an-app-with-gen-ai.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/robots-and-humans-working-together.png" alt="A vibrant celebration between a human and a robot" /></p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kNiY-HYaqUc">I gave a talk in the summer of 2023</a> about how the chatbot is just an interface, and not always the best interface. Well, the chatbot obsession rages on. I want to show that Large Language Models, Image Diffusers and other AI models can augment the applications we use today using interfaces we’re already familiar with.</p>

<p>To explore this idea, I plan to build a comic book studio. A browser based application that lets you write and illustrate your own comic book, but with the help of Generative AI. Here’s a few reasons why I keep coming back to this idea:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Comic books are a marriage of visual art and storytelling. That gives me the opportunity to use both generative text and generative images.</li>
  <li>Each comic is made of smaller elements, like pages and panels and speech bubbles. Today’s models do better with small tasks.</li>
  <li>It seems fun. AI can be used in SaaS apps, or enterprise tools, but let’s get creative.</li>
</ul>

<p>Personally, I’ve never really been into comic books, but it should be a good way to experiment with GenAI in traditional interfaces.</p>

<hr />

<p>I have over a decade of experience building applications. My understanding of software is through the lens of web applications. This project is an attempt to merge that experience with practical uses of Generative AI. Here are some things I hope to demonstrate and explore over the coming weeks:</p>

<h2 id="product-considerations">Product considerations</h2>

<h3 id="bookmarks-revisions-and-short-feedback-loops">Bookmarks, revisions and short feedback loops</h3>
<p>In my experience with GenAI, you rarely get what you want on the first try. But each prompt builds on the last until you get something that kind of works. At times, I’ll get something that works for my needs, but I continue to experiment only to realize my best result was 10 prompts ago. Sometimes I want to start over after some experimentation.</p>

<p>It should be easy for the user to iterate, bookmark promising results, restore past revisions, build on past successes and, if needed, start over.</p>

<h3 id="ai-is-a-tool-not-a-replacement">AI is a tool, not a replacement</h3>
<p>My goal is to build an interface first for the user. Then build an AI collaborator that can do things on the user’s behalf. With our focus on bookmarks and revisions, we can always undo what the AI has done. This keeps the user in control, and demonstrates how to augment an existing application interface with GenAI functionality. I’m not convinced this is the only way, and I’m likely to put some “magic” into the app, but I think this is a good perspective.</p>

<h3 id="define-a-step-by-step-workflow">Define a step by step workflow</h3>
<p>I imagine different layouts for different activities. Storytelling is set up separate from page layout is separate from panel layout. This keeps the tasks small a manageable for today’s generative models. It allows you to iterate your prompts at each stage. And smaller tasks for the AI also means quicker feedback to the user.</p>

<h3 id="there-can-still-be-a-chatbot">There can still be a chatbot</h3>
<p>I’m actually really excited the way that OpenAI has incorporated things like functions and the ability to write and run code. Chat functionality is going to be a lower priority for this project, but I’m not taking the stance that chatbots have no place. Just that they’re restrictive as the sole way to interact.</p>

<h2 id="technical-considerations">Technical considerations</h2>

<h3 id="building-for-experimentation">Building for experimentation</h3>
<p>Results from generative AI are still hard to predict. Developers need to try out different models and prompts and technologies. They need to be able to upgrade as new things come out. I think that modularity and an agile mindset are going to be a good start, but I hope to have more strategies by the end of the project.</p>

<h3 id="user-feedback-strategies">User Feedback strategies</h3>
<p>AI is trained. It tries to do more of what you like, and less of what you don’t like. But in order to train, you need data.</p>

<p>The first step is keeping track of what users like and dislike. I think existing user analytics tools are going to get us started. But we also need to hold on to the AI results that the user keeps, as well as things the user discarded.</p>

<p>Secondly, data needs to be fed back into the AI. This might be manually updating prompts based on what users are struggling with. It might be fine tuning models with the results they landed on. It might be more manual RLHF done by someone on the development team. I’m going to try to cover a few strategies, but there also are good resources already for creating better prompts from known examples or fine tuning models.</p>

<h3 id="can-we-work-toward-the-rails-of-genai">Can we work toward the Rails of GenAI?</h3>

<p>Django and Ruby on Rails were both developed by building out an application, and then generalizing the architecture. Whatever I build is going to be really rough, but I hope to learn enough that I could start to see how a GenAI framework might help other developers build their own GenAI applications. And I would love for other developers to help me with that vision.</p>

<h3 id="copyright-and-content-filtering">Copyright and Content filtering</h3>
<p>This is the last item for a reason. I’m not particularly well versed in copyright. It’s also not clear to me how, or even what we should be filtering. But I don’t want to pretend that these models came out of a vacuum. They’re trained on the text and images that real humans put effort into and published to the web in good faith. And I don’t want to wildly miss user expectations on text and images that could be considered offensive. So, I’d like to figure out how to touch on this. Let me know if you have read some great takes lately, on either copyright or content filtering in AI.</p>

<hr />

<p>I’m still at the beginning of this journey. I don’t have it all worked out yet. You’ll get to see some paths that work, and some paths that don’t. But if this is interesting to you, stick with me.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Emerging AI interfaces: Beyond the chatbot</title><link href="https://www.bluepail.co//2023/08/22/ai-interafaces-beyond-chatbot.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Emerging AI interfaces: Beyond the chatbot" /><published>2023-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.bluepail.co//2023/08/22/ai-interafaces-beyond-chatbot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.bluepail.co//2023/08/22/ai-interafaces-beyond-chatbot.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>The chatbot demos well.</strong></p>

<p>I’m talking, of course, about ChatGPT. We’re not used to having a conversation with our computer. At least not a satisfying one. We’ve become more familiar with awkward phone systems that seem so proud of themselves. How many times a day are you swearing at your smart speaker? It seems like things haven’t improved since Clippy. 📎</p>

<p>And now they have. Chatting with a computer is now something people want to do. They’ve found all kinds of useful and productive new ways to work. <strong>But I don’t think that chat is the best way to communicate for every situation.</strong></p>

<p>Imagine sitting down in a restaurant where there is no menu. Not even a QR code. The waiter asks you what you want. In your best case scenario, you have an existing craving and can describe it well enough that it will play the telephone game back to the kitchen. I’m not saying this can’t work. You could probably get used to it. But is it better? Would you prefer it?</p>

<p>But lets talk about the web. <strong>We can use familiar UI to help users get value from generative AI.</strong> I want to breakdown two web applications that have been built around the value of LLMs, but they are not chat windows.</p>

<h2 id="goblin-tools">Goblin Tools</h2>
<p><a href="goblin.tools">goblin.tools</a></p>

<p>I discovered <a href="https://skyhook.be/">Bram De Buyser’s</a> Goblin Tools from a tiktok that my wife sent me. It is a set of simple tools with simple interfaces to help with communication style and organization. Let’s walk through one of them, and see how the interface adds to the experience.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/1_b8lWKi1lCjaeLXAWmo5vSA.png" alt="Alt" title="Bring your true self, and find the appropriate mask. A tool for your tone." /></p>

<p><strong>Formalizer</strong> is a tool to change the tone of something you’ve written. You might have received a text or an email where your initial reaction was not going to work. Or maybe you have a tendency to sound passive. Well, write in your voice and let Formalizer convert it to a tone that better fits the situation.
There’s really only a handful of elements on the page. Input text, output text, and a couple of configuration options in between.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/1_J-eS5Fn9eOWVFq9cGnmWjQ.png" alt="Alt" /></p>

<p>Maybe you’ve done this exact thing with ChatGPT. You’ve asked it to take something you’ve written and prompted it to change the tone to something else. So why complicate it?</p>

<p>These familiar UI elements, a dropdown and a slider, provide a clear interaction in a context where language is already difficult. You don’t have to provide the menu. You don’t have to build empathy for the recipient of your message, nor do you have to build empathy for the chatbot.</p>

<p><em>And a quick shoutout to the copy button at the bottom, a standard fixture even in the world of chatbots.</em></p>

<h2 id="rytr">Rytr</h2>
<p><a href="rytr.me">rytr.me</a></p>

<p>Personally, I have used chatGPT to help me organize a stream of consciousness, and to expand on idea that I’m not ready to communicate. I’ve even had it write some dialogue for a book that I’ll probably never write. But I don’t love the copying and pasting to and from google docs. So I found Rytr.</p>

<p>Rytr has a very paired down text editor with basic formatting. But it has little entry points into the power of a large language model scattered throughout it’s UI.</p>

<p>It starts with the sidebar. It has a whole host of use cases and tones to get you started. Then you enter a few more details about what you want written, and it writes those things for you.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/1_9gx-zNtRzHucHr6T1DlHow.gif" alt="Alt" /></p>

<p>If the content needs adjustments, you can select specific parts of the text and have Rytr make adjustments for you. There are pre-determined changes you can make to your text, or you can even enter your own prompt.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/1_dZrRbd8oKVwX-Ta7i8dNyg.png" alt="Alt" /></p>

<p>And this gives you flexibility in your workflow. If the blank canvas is intimidating, have it get you started. If your first draft flows out of you, but then you get stuck, the AI can provide suggestions on how to polish it.</p>

<hr />

<p>These are just a couple examples of web applications built around generative AI. They utilize known interface elements, like drop-downs, sliders and text selections to keep things intuitive. Users don’t need to learn prompt engineering to utilize this new tool.</p>

<p>The chat window is here to stay. We’ve been directed to chat windows to solve support problems for years now. Microsoft is building chat into Office and even Windows.</p>

<p>But what about the people who want to use these new tools, who would see real value from using these tools, but they don’t know how to engage. They might be intimidated by the term “prompt engineering”. They may just feel like they don’t have time to learn a new skill. Chat as an interface is not always intuitive, and often intimidating.</p>

<p>If you’re a UX designer, product manager or application developer, keep an eye out for generative AI interfaces popping up. Think about how you can add them to your own offerings.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The chatbot demos well.]]></summary></entry></feed>